<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>The Life of a Radar</title>
 <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://ryanbigg.com"/>
 <updated>2010-12-28T09:36:41+10:00</updated>
 <id>http://ryanbigg.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Ryan Bigg</name>
   <email>radarlistener@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Converting from WordPress to Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/converting-from-wordpress-to-jekyll"/>
   <updated>2010-12-27T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/converting-from-wordpress-to-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I converted this blog from WordPress to Jekyll, thanks to some prompting from <a href='http://twitter.com/lenary'>Sam Elliott</a> and <a href='http://twitter.com/rohitarondekar'>Rohit Arondekar</a>. All in all, the process wasn&#8217;t actually all that painful. What triggered this whole thing was three factors:</p>

<ul>
<li>My Slicehost server crashed, possibly due to some intense load I was getting from the <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/ubuntu-ruby-rvm-rails-and-you'>Ubuntu, Ruby, RVM, Rails and You</a> post I wrote (whilst under the influence of delicious cider).</li>

<li>When the server rebooted, I was unable to boot Apache2 back up because <em>somebody</em> (read: me) had fucked with sqlite3 to try to get his IRC bot to work on the server.</li>

<li>Slicehost charged me $38/month for a 512MB box. Linode charges about half that for the same thing. Fuck Slicehost.</li>
</ul>

<p>So off I went on a magical journey to fix these three problems.</p>

<h3 id='never_work_on_live_systems'>Never work on live systems</h3>

<p>A rule that every developer has to learn the hard way (be it from anywhere to their own system up to a website with a couple of hundred users) is that you <strong>never ever, ever, ever work on live systems because something will go terribly, terribly wrong</strong>. The second rule that every developer learns is <strong>backups, motherfucker, do you have them?</strong>. So when I had 3 years of posts that I didn&#8217;t want to lose I obeyed these two rules.</p>

<h3 id='wordpress_conversion'>Wordpress conversion</h3>

<p>First task was to take an SQL backup from the WordPress install that I had and move it over to my own system. Next, I imported this SQL into a local install of MySQL and made sure it was the latest-and-greatest. Sure, enough it was. Rohit had pointed me at the <a href='https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/blog-migrations'>Blog migrations wiki page</a> for Jekyll and it had what appeared to be clear instructions for WordPress there.</p>

<p>So I cloned the <a href='http://github.com/mojombo/jekyll'>Jekyll</a> project into my <code>~/Sites/gems</code> folder and ran just the wordpress commands because I have tunnel vision when reading documentation (note: not my real username and password):</p>

<pre><code>$ export DB=ryanbigg
$ export USER=lolno 
$ export PASS=nopass4u 
$ ruby -r &#39;~/Sites/gems/jekyll/lib/jekyll/migrators/wordpress&#39; -e &#39;Jekyll::WordPress.process( &quot;#{ENV[&quot;DB&quot;]}&quot;, &quot;#{ENV[&quot;USER&quot;]}&quot;, &quot;#{ENV[&quot;PASS&quot;]}&quot;)&#39;</code></pre>

<p>To my surprise, it worked. I had a whole bunch of <code>_posts</code> files representing the posts in my system.</p>

<h3 id='booting_jekyll'>Booting Jekyll</h3>

<p>I installed the <code>jekyll</code> gem itself using <code>gem install jekyll</code> and then ran <code>jekyll --server</code> and it threw up a ton of &#8220;errors&#8221;, which actually turned out to be warnings about my ability to sometimes intersperse invalid HTML / Markdown with valid Markdown (or the other way around). When I went to http://localhost:4000 I got a 403 error. So I checked out other Jekyll blogs like <a href='http://github.com/qrush/litanyagainstfear'>Nick Quaranto's litanyagainstfear repository</a> to see what I was missing. I instantly came across the <a href='https://github.com/qrush/litanyagainstfear/blob/master/index.html'>index.html</a> file in this repository and &#8220;borrowed&#8221; it for my own blog, turning it into <a href='https://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com/blob/master/index.html'>what's now here</a>. I choose to only show the last 25 posts because everything before that is ancient history. The links to them will still work, but I&#8217;m just not showing them in the archive list to conserve space.</p>

<h3 id='stylin'>Stylin&#8217;</h3>

<p>The next thing I needed to do was to create a <a href='https://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com/blob/master/_layouts/default.html'>default.html layout</a> file in the <code>_layouts</code> folder to style this new home page of mine. I created a <code>css</code> folder at the root of the project and put in <a href='https://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com/blob/master/css/style.css'>`style.css`</a> and got to work styling it. I wanted something a little more lightweight than the old theme and I think what I came up with was alright. This morning I added a <a href='https://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com/blob/master/css/mobile.css'>`mobile.css`</a> which should format the blog just fine for mobile screens. It looks great on my iPhone 4.</p>

<h3 id='comments'>Comments</h3>

<p>I wanted to keep the comments from the WordPress site and Rohit recommended Disqus as a way to do that. I installed the <a href='http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/disqus-comment-system/'>WordPress plugin</a> for it and followed the bouncing ball and had my comments exported to Disqus in no time. I needed to add the following to the <a href='https://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com/blob/0c30ab8b5b9721b16fa125d94270d797d4eb556e/_layouts/post.html#L16-30'>post layout</a> to support the Disqus comment system. The <code>wordpress_id</code> field is the &#8220;secret sauce&#8221; here for how Disqus knows which post links up to what comments. The only caveat I&#8217;ve been informed about for Disqus is that the comments won&#8217;t be indexed by Google because they&#8217;re loaded via a JavaScript request, but I can tolerate that. Any useful information I would put in a post, probably.</p>

<h3 id='wordpress_pages'>WordPress pages</h3>

<p>To convert over the pages from WordPress that weren&#8217;t posts I&#8217;ve copied the source of them (such as the <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/about-me.html'>About me</a> page) and put them as static HTML files in the root of the project. When Jekyll compiles the site, these are copied over to the <code>_site</code> directory.</p>

<h3 id='deployment'>Deployment</h3>

<p>Currently going via the low-tech method of an SSH + <code>git pull</code> on the server, but hoping to switch to a commit hook in the future.</p>

<h3 id='benefits'>Benefits</h3>

<p>The benefits are many. My posts are now <a href='http://github.com/radar/ryanbigg.com'>open source</a> which means that if people find problems with them that can send in pull requests, but that&#8217;s just a pipe dream probably.</p>

<p>The main benefit is the speed. On the vanilla WordPress install I had I was lucky to get 2 requests per second for the home page. With Jekyll, I&#8217;m getting about 2,300 reqests per second. This is due to the fact all my posts are static assets now. I think I could double this if I <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2009/06/how-to-make-your-rails-application-578-times-faster/'>switched to Nginx</a>, which I plan on doing when I don&#8217;t have a use for the PHP version anymore.</p>

<p>I also get to write my posts the way I like to: Markdown + HTML. No crummy little editor window, I can do it all from within TextMate.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m really liking Jekyll as lightweight alternative to WordPress and it&#8217;s great to finally be off a PHP-based system. I mean, if Ruby is so good <a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Not_Invented_Here'>why would I be using a PHP based system?</a></p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ubuntu, Ruby, RVM, Rails, and You</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/ubuntu-ruby-rvm-rails-and-you"/>
   <updated>2010-12-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/ubuntu-ruby-rvm-rails-and-you</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<strong>This beginner's guide will set up with Ruby 1.9.2, RVM and Rails 3.0.3 and is specifically written for Ubuntu 10.10, but will probably work on many other operating systems. YMMV.</strong><h2>Under no circumstance should you install Ruby, Rubygems or any Ruby-related packages from apt-get. This system is out-dated and leads to major headaches. Avoid it for Ruby-related packages. We do Ruby, we know what's best. Trust us.</h2>
<p>Still not convinced? <a href='http://news.ycombinator.org/item?id=2039438'>Read this</a>.</p>

<p>This guide will go through installing the <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com'>RVM (Ruby Version Manager)</a>, then a version of Ruby (1.9.2), then <a href='http://rubyonrails.org'>Rails</a> and finally <a href='http://gembundler.com'>Bundler</a>.</p>

<p>By the end of this guide, you will have these things installed and have some very, very easy ways to manage gem dependencies for your different applications / libraries, as well as having multiple Ruby versions installed and usable all at once.</p>

<p>We assume you have <code>sudo</code> access to your machine, and that you have an understanding of the basic concepts of Ruby, such as &#8220;What is Rubygems?&#8221; and more importantly &#8220;How do I turn this computer-thing on?&#8221;. This knowledge can be garnered by reading the first chapter of <a href='http://manning.com/black2'>any Ruby book</a>.</p>
<h3>Housekeeping</h3>
<p>First of all, we&#8217;re going to run <code>sudo apt-get update</code> so that we have the latest sources on our box so that we don&#8217;t run into any package-related issues, such as not being able to install some packages.</p>

<p>Next, we&#8217;re going to install <a href='http://git-scm.org'>Git (a version control system)</a> and <code>curl</code> which are both required to install and use RVM, and <code>build-essential</code> which is required to compile Ruby versions, amongst other compilable things. To install these three packages we use this command:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install build-essential git-core curl</code></pre>
<h3>RVM</h3>
<p>RVM is a <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com'>Ruby Version Manager</a> created by Wayne E. Seguin and is extremely helpful for installing and managing many different versions of Ruby all at once. Sometimes you could be working on a project that requires an older (1.8.7) version of Ruby but also need a new version (1.9.2) for one of your newer projects. This is a problem that RVM solves beautifully.</p>

<p>Another situation could be that you want to have different sets of gems on the same version of Ruby but don&#8217;t want to have to do deal with Gem Conflict Hell. RVM has <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com/gemsets/basics/'>gemsets</a> for this. <strong>This is a feature you wouldn't have if you used the packaged Ruby</strong>.</p>

<p>We&#8217;re going to use it to install only one version of Ruby, but we can <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com'>consult the documentation</a> if we want to install a different version of Ruby.</p>

<p>With <code>git-core</code> and <code>curl</code> installed we&#8217;ll be able to install RVM with this command:</p>

<pre><code>bash &lt; &lt;( curl http://rvm.beginrescueend.com/releases/rvm-install-head )</code></pre>

<p>The beautiful part of this is that it installs Ruby to our home directory, providing a sandboxed environment just for us.</p>

<p>Once that&#8217;s done, we&#8217;re going to need to add a line to <code>~/.bashrc</code> file (the file responsible for setting up our bash session) which will load RVM:</p>

<pre><code>echo &#39;[[ -s &quot;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&quot; ]] &amp;&amp; source &quot;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&quot;&#39; &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc </code></pre>

<p>Then we&#8217;ll need to reload the <code>~/.bashrc</code> file which we can do with this small command:</p>

<pre><code>. ~/.bashrc</code></pre>

<p>The next command we run will tell us what other packages we need to install for Ruby to work:</p>

<pre><code>rvm notes
...
# For Ruby (MRI &amp; ree)  you should install the following OS dependencies:
ruby: aptitude install build-essential bison openssl libreadline6 libreadline6-dev
curl git-core zlib1g zlib1g-dev libssl-dev libyaml-dev libsqlite3-0
libsqlite3-dev sqlite3 libxml2-dev libxslt-dev autoconf</code></pre>

<p>A couple of these packages we&#8217;ve already installed, such as <code>git-core</code> and <code>curl</code>. They won&#8217;t be re-installed again.</p>

<p>These packages will lessen the pain when we&#8217;re working with Ruby. For example, the <code>libssl-dev</code> package will make OpenSSL support in Ruby work, <code>libsqlite3-0</code> and <code>libsqlite3-dev</code> are required for the <code>sqlite3-ruby</code> gem and the <code>libxml2-dev</code> and <code>libxslt-dev</code> packages are required for the <code>nokogiri</code> gem. Let&#8217;s install all these packages now using this command written all on a single line:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install build-essential bison openssl libreadline6 libreadline6-dev curl git-core zlib1g
zlib1g-dev libssl-dev libyaml-dev libsqlite3-0 libsqlite3-dev sqlite3 libxml2-dev libxslt-dev autoconf</code></pre>

<p>Now our Ruby lives will be as painless as possible.</p>
<h3>Ruby</h3>
<p>With RVM and these packages we can install Ruby 1.9.2:</p>

<pre><code>rvm install 1.9.2</code></pre>

<p>This command will take a couple of minutes, so grab your $DRINKOFCHOICE and go outside or something. Once it&#8217;s done, we&#8217;ll have Ruby 1.9.2 installed. To begin using it we can use this lovely command:</p>

<pre><code>rvm use 1.9.2</code></pre>

<p>Are we using 1.9.2? You betcha:</p>

<pre><code>ruby -v
ruby 1.9.2p136 (2010-12-25 revision 30365) [x86_64-linux]</code></pre>

<p>Or, even better, would be to make this the <em>default</em> for our user! Oooh, yes!</p>

<pre><code>rvm --default use 1.9.2</code></pre>

<p>Now whenever we open a new bash session for this user we&#8217;ll have Ruby available for us to use! Yay!</p>
<h3>Rails</h3>
<p>Now that RVM and a version of Ruby is installed, we can install Rails. Because RVM is installed to our home directory, we don&#8217;t need to use that nasty <code>sudo</code> to install things; we&#8217;ve got write-access! To install the Rails gem we&#8217;ll run this command:</p>

<pre><code>gem install rails</code></pre>

<p>This will install the <code>rails</code> gem and the other 22 gems that it and its dependencies depend on, including Bundler.</p>
<h3>MySQL</h3>
<p>If you&#8217;re planning on using the <code>mysql2</code> gem for your application then you&#8217;ll want to install the <code>libmysqlclient16-dev</code> package before you do that. Without it, you&#8217;ll get an error when the gem tries to compile its native extensions:</p>

<pre><code>Building native extensions.  This could take a while...
ERROR:  Error installing mysql2:
	ERROR: Failed to build gem native extension.

/home/ryan/.rvm/rubies/ruby-1.9.2-p136/bin/ruby extconf.rb
checking for rb_thread_blocking_region()... yes
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
checking for main() in -lm... yes
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
checking for main() in -lz... yes
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
checking for main() in -lsocket... no
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
checking for main() in -lnsl... yes
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
checking for main() in -lmygcc... no
checking for mysql_query() in -lmysqlclient... no
*** extconf.rb failed ***
Could not create Makefile due to some reason, probably lack of
necessary libraries and/or headers.  Check the mkmf.log file for more
details.  You may need configuration options.</code></pre>
<h3>PostgreSQL</h3>
<p>Similar to the <code>mysql2</code> gem&#8217;s error above, you&#8217;ll also get an error with the <code>pg</code> gem if you don&#8217;t have the <code>libpq-dev</code> package installed you&#8217;ll get this error:</p>

<pre><code>    Building native extensions.  This could take a while...
ERROR:  Error installing pg:
	ERROR: Failed to build gem native extension.

/home/ryan/.rvm/rubies/ruby-1.9.2-p136/bin/ruby extconf.rb
checking for pg_config... no
checking for libpq-fe.h... no
Can&#39;t find the &#39;libpq-fe.h header
*** extconf.rb failed ***
Could not create Makefile due to some reason, probably lack of
necessary libraries and/or headers.  Check the mkmf.log file for more
details.  You may need configuration options.</code></pre>
<h3>Fin.</h3>
<p>And that&#8217;s it! Now you&#8217;ve got a Ruby environment you can use to write your (first?) Rails application in with such minimal effort. A good read after this would be the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org'>official guides for Ruby on Rails</a>. Or perhaps the documentation on the <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com'>RVM site</a> which goes into using things such as <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com/gemsets/basics/'>gemsets</a> and the exceptionally helpful <a href='http://rvm.beginrescueend.com/workflow/rvmrc/#project'>per-project .rvmrc file</a>. A quick way to generate an <code>.rvmrc</code> file is to run a command like this inside the project</p>

<pre><code>rvm use 1.9.2@rails3 --rvmrc</code></pre>

<p>RVM is such a powerful tool and comes in handy for day-to-day Ruby development. Use it, and not the packages from apt to live a life of development luxury.</p>
<h4>Credits</h4>
<p>Thanks to <a href='http://twitter.com/krainboltgreene'>krainboltgreene</a> for pointing out that the guide needed to install the packages specified by rvm notes. He&#8217;s got a similar <a href='http://krainboltgreene.github.com/l/3'>write up here for Ubuntu 10.04</a>. Some of the instructions in this guide were &#8220;inspired&#8221; by that post.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Rails routing and automatic assumptions</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/rails-routing-and-automatic-assumptions"/>
   <updated>2010-12-19T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/rails-routing-and-automatic-assumptions</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night while working on chapter 12 for <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>Rails 3 in Action</a> I stumbled across an interesting problem detailed in <a href='https://gist.github.com/746414'>this gist</a>. The problem I was seeing is that the <code>edit_admin_user_path</code> route <em>was not</em> failing, while the <code>admin_user_permissions_path</code> path <em>was</em> failing.</p>

<p>I had my suspicions to why the first link worked and spent the remainder of last night digging through my favourite bit of Rails and Rails related source(ry): Action Dispatch and rack-mount. I didn&#8217;t figure it all completely out until after a good night&#8217;s sleep. It wasn&#8217;t until I saw pixeltrix&#8217;s comment on the Gist this morning that it all clicked.</p>

<p>I knew from a while ago that sometimes Rails will just <em>know</em> what to put as the <code>:id</code> part of a route and I never did bother questioning how that part of Rails works until last night. It turns out that Action Dispatch (and by extension, rack-mount) are very intelligent in the way that they build routes. Take the <code>edit_admin_user_path</code> route for example. This requires two parameters: <code>:account_id</code> and <code>:id</code>, representing an account and user object respectively. The routing code doesn&#8217;t <em>care</em> what arguments are passed in here, only the order of them. All it does is call <code>to_param</code> on the objects to extract the segments for the routes. So when you do this:</p>
<pre>
   edit_admin_user_path(@user)
</pre>
<p>But the order of the parameters in the URL are <code>:account_id</code> and then <code>:id</code>, Rails will assume that the first object is meant for the <code>:account_id</code> parameter. How does it work out the <code>:id</code> parameter then? It&#8217;s not passed into the helper, so instead it&#8217;s gathered from the current request&#8217;s parameters. Therefore, this helper generates a URL such as <code>/2/users/2/edit</code> inadvertently. We can change this to be simply:</p>
<pre>
   edit_admin_user_path
</pre>
<p>Then Rails will assume that we want the current <code>:account_id</code> and <code>:id</code> from the current request, making our code much shorter, compared to what we&#8217;d have to do if this feature didn&#8217;t exist:</p>
<pre>
  edit_admin_user_path(@account, @user)
</pre>
<p>The <code>admin_user_permissions_path(@user)</code> helper throws an error because it expects to receive both a <code>:account_id</code> and <code>:user_id</code> parameter. Without the <code>:user_id</code> parameter available or passed in to the helper, rack-mount won&#8217;t know how to generate this URL and will raise a &#8220;No route matches&#8221; error.</p>

<p>Oh, and I also <a href='http://twitter.com/ryanbigg/status/16104049640210432'>offered a free copy of Rails 3 in Action</a> to the person who helped me solve this issue, but it was really a team effort. alindeman, pixeltrix and pacsoe all get free, signed dead-tree copies when the book&#8217;s done. Thanks lads.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Asking Questions The Right Way</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/asking-questions-the-right-way"/>
   <updated>2010-12-16T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/asking-questions-the-right-way</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time on <a href='http://stackoverflow.com/users/15245/ryan-bigg'>Stack Overflow</a> answering Ruby and Rails questions, but also venturing into other areas such as git or html and so on. I&#8217;ve answered over 400 questions on there and recently broke 8,000 reputation points. As of this posting, I&#8217;ve been there 32 days in a row.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s safe to say I&#8217;m a tad addicted.</p>

<p>I really enjoy answering <a href='http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4433823/testing-reject-if-in-anaf'>interesting questions</a> asked by the huge number of people who use the site, possibly mainly because I get a &#8220;reward&#8221; for it most of the time in that my reputation &#8220;score&#8221; increases when someone presses the upvote arrow or the accept checkmark. Or possibly also because I learn stuff like that model classes in Rails 3 have a <code>nested_attribute_options</code> method on them which allows access to the configuration for all <code>accepts_nested_attribute_for</code> in that model. Or possibly both.</p>

<p>What I don&#8217;t enjoy though is decrypting <a href='http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4456254/why-dont-i-get-a-method-error'>weird questions</a>. These questions usually follow the same MO. The user begins by declaring something vague like &#8220;my code isn&#8217;t working&#8221; and then follows it up with a &#8220;plz can any1 help?&#8221; or something similar. Sure, they&#8217;re probably new to the language. So it&#8217;s up to show them the proper way to ask a question for Ruby.</p>
<h3>Step 0: Smart questions</h3>
<p>Read of <a href='http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html'>"How to Ask Questions The Smart Way" by Eric Steven Raymond</a>. It pretty much covers every single possible permutation of asking a question. Follow this guide, and you cannot do any wrong.</p>
<h3>Step 1: Show us the code</h3>
<p>Generally when I help somebody solve the issue it&#8217;s good to get some background on how they got to that particular problem. For me, the best kind of background is some actual code. In most cases the problem is right there and obvious right away and just by looking at it anybody who knows the language should be able to help you solve it.</p>

<p>If it&#8217;s an IRC channel, a user can paste a single line of code into an IRC channel, but generally the preferred method is either a <a href='http://gist.github.com'>Gist</a> or a <a href='http://pastie.org'>Pastie</a> (when it&#8217;s up). Be sure to mention that you&#8217;re going to need the HTTP URL from those services, not the Git URL. Also, don&#8217;t encourage use of <a href='http://pastebin.org'>Pastebin</a>, because it&#8217;s got ugly syntax highlighting and there&#8217;s a pretty strong rumour going around that it may be Demonspawn.</p>
<h3>Step 2: Show us the stacktrace</h3>
<p>If the code doesn&#8217;t show the breakage clearly, then the next port of call is the stacktrace associated with the error. Again, <a href='http://gist.github.com'>Gist</a> or <a href='http://pastie.org'>Pastie</a> are perfect for these. Take <a href='https://gist.github.com/3a45806f5391505530a5'>this gist</a> for example. If the user shows just the first line of the error then we&#8217;d have no context to go on. The stacktrace provides that context and from that we can determine they&#8217;re using a deprecated-in-Rails-3 method and that they should probably delete that file.</p>
<h3>Step 3: Explain what is being attempted</h3>
<p>If all else fails, then perhaps there&#8217;s a bigger issue at hand. Perhaps the code can be designed in a better fashion. By talking over the issue with other people they may have unique views on how to do it in a better fashion. Talking through a tough problem with other people who have been there before is really the best way to work out what the right way to do it is.</p>

<p>With the <code>MethodError</code> StackOverflow question it would be helpful for a person wanting to help to know why that person wants a <code>MethodError</code> exception rather than a <code>NoMethodError</code> exception. What&#8217;s the end goal?</p>

<p>By seeing these three simple things, we as helpers are more enabled to help those who are asking for our help.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Writing Process</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/the-writing-process"/>
   <updated>2010-12-11T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/the-writing-process</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a while since I&#8217;ve videoblogged about the progress on Rails 3 in Action and I&#8217;m in that kind of mood tonight, but can&#8217;t be bothered turning on the light and setting up for that, so instead you&#8217;ll get it in text version.</p>

<p>This week on Tuesday, I caught up with Mark Ryall for lunch and he asked what the writing process was like. I explained it to him and that&#8217;s definitely not the first time I&#8217;ve explained it to somebody, but nevertheless still tried to make it sound interesting. There&#8217;s a couple of key points I&#8217;d like to use this post to go into greater detail about.</p>
<h3>There are no montages</h3>
<p>Ever seen Rocky I? It has a great training montage where through some clever cutting we see Rocky train for the big fight. He&#8217;s running through fields, drinking raw eggs, and finally climbing a huge flight of stairs and then &#8220;dancing&#8221; because he was victorious.</p>

<p>In the real world, there are no montages. I wake up in the morning and I think about how much I&#8217;d like to get done in a day. Sometimes I do that, sometimes I exceed expectation and sometimes I fail. But the main point is that I&#8217;m at least giving it a go, every single day. If I&#8217;m not writing, then I&#8217;m at least thinking about what I would write about, how the pieces all fit together. Perseverance is definitely a non-optional thing when it comes to writing a book. I focus on planning out a section and then writing it. Sometimes during the writing of it, I discover some oversight in a previous paragraph and jump back to fix it. If I don&#8217;t fix it, then I&#8217;ve got my awesome review team which will point out mistakes, which takes me on to my second point.</p>
<h3>Get a posse</h3>
<p>The review team so far have filed 870 notes for the book. Now, whilst this may seem like a lot, there&#8217;s a whole wall-o&#8217;-text there, some 130,000+ words so far. Many of these notes where stuff like places where I use &#8220;ran&#8221; rather than &#8220;run&#8221; or where sentences would have better wording. Then there were notes as well saying that the reviewer got lost in the text or that a code example is missing a character or overflows. Without these reviewers, I would not have been able to solve these notes as quickly as I have been, and I hope that they&#8217;ll stick with me until it&#8217;s over.</p>

<p>How do these reviewers file the notes? That&#8217;s the third point.</p>
<h3>The tools for writing a programming book, suck</h3>
<p>Surely, somebody has solved this issue. Unfortunately for myself, that somebody isn&#8217;t my publisher. I&#8217;m hand-writing the book in XML which goes a little like this:</p>
<pre>
&lt;informalexample id="ch12_152"&gt;
  &lt;programlisting id="ch12_153"&gt;
    &lt;![CDATA[create_table :accounts_users, :id =&gt; false do |t|
      t.string :account_id
      t.string :user_id
      t.boolean :admin, :default =&gt; false
    end
    
    remove_column :users, :admin
    ]]&gt;
  &lt;/programlisting&gt;
&lt;/informalexample&gt;
</pre>
<p>I&#8217;ve got TextMate macros for that so I just type <code>in[tab]</code> for it to generate the <code>informalexample</code> and nested <code>programlisting</code> tags, with the <code>id</code> attributes filled in at a later time by <a href='https://gist.github.com/737322'>a script I've written myself</a>. That in itself was an interesting problem to solve. Each and every single element in the document needs a unique ID, but you can&#8217;t just go ahead and number every single element in order: you have to be considerate of the fact that some elements may already have ids. If that&#8217;s the case, then you find the &#8220;biggest&#8221; id and just add +1 to that for every single new element.</p>

<p>Why do these elements need IDs? Because of how Manning&#8217;s review tool works. My editor and I both have access to a tool that we can log into and leave notes for the book. These notes relate to an element based on that element&#8217;s ID so even if the <em>content</em> of the element changes after the note has been left, we still know what element that refers to. The IDs for that particular system are something like <code>_432_4125_3843</code>, where the first number is the book id, the second number the chapter id and the third number the element number for that chapter. I prefer my naming schema, to be perfectly honest.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s a small problem with the tool my editor and I use: only we have access to it. For very good reason too. Anybody who has access to it gets to see every single other book written by Manning, which is probably not the best for security reasons there. Also, this tool requires me to use SVN (wherein a part of me dies every time that happens), as well as <a href='https://skitch.com/ryanbigg/rrxji/a'>an interface that is from many, many years ago.</a> To update a chapter, I must go into this interface and click on every chapter, scroll to the very bottom of the page, press the &#8220;Latest&#8221; radio button and press &#8220;Update&#8221;. Then once the request is done, I get no clear notification if something has gone wrong. It&#8217;s all very luck-based.</p>

<p>One Saturday, I got tired of doing this. I knew I could code something far, far greater. Hell, I was/am writing a book on Rails 3, why not build another Rails application to help in that process? That&#8217;s how Twist was born. On a single Saturday (ok, and some minor upkeep during some down time).</p>
<h3>Twist</h3>
<p>Twist is a Rails 3.0.3 application which currently has about 40 users. Each of these users can log into the system and leave notes for any element in any chapter and also see notes left by other users. Collaborative editing is the future, man. I can log into the system and see exactly what every other user sees, except I have one extra ability: I can close notes. Ideally I would like to have three stages for notes: Open, Complete and Closed so that people can check to see if the note is to their satisfaction, but I haven&#8217;t seen any large use for that yet. It&#8217;s just a nice-to-have.</p>

<p>So how does Twist get the book then? That Saturday was fever-pitch coding. I host the book on GitHub (quite probably my favourite online service that&#8217;s not a bank), and GitHub has Post-Receive Hooks which trigger when the repository is pushed to. With these, I can send a payload of a commit to any URL I desire. This payload contains information such as what files were added, modified or removed during the commits that have happened for that push. So that&#8217;s what Twist uses. It parses the payload, downloads the XML for the chapters and parses it all and stores it in a database structure that, simply put, goes like this:</p>
<pre>
  Book -&lt; Chapters -&lt; Revisions -&lt; Sections -&lt; Elements &gt;- Notes &gt;- Users
</pre>
<p>Every time I push a change to GitHub, it&#8217;s instantly available for the reviewers to see. No SVN or shitty interface bullshit. When reviewers visit a section it&#8217;s rendered right from the database. If it had a lot of traffic, sure, I&#8217;d cache it. It just doesn&#8217;t need it right now. One of my favourite features which I added recently was the ability to close notes through commit messages using a message such as &#8220;Fixed messed-up code sample - Finishes #711&#8221;, ala GitHub Issues. Oh, and <a href='https://skitch.com/ryanbigg/rrxkb/twist.ryanbigg.com-1.2.4'>it looks like this</a>. Hat-tip to Ben Hoskings for the protips on things like the line and paragraph spacing.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s one thing I haven&#8217;t been able to solve yet: testing the code samples.</p>
<h3>How do you know it works?</h3>
<p>One thing that bugs me with this writing process is that I have no solid clue if the code I&#8217;m writing actually works. A lo-fi way I&#8217;ve worked out of solving this is to write the code for the application as I&#8217;m writing the book. Make it work in the application and then it&#8217;s a matter of simply copying over the code from the application into the book. My main problem with that is that code and output can both change. I don&#8217;t know how yet to test this cleanly &#8211; and I&#8217;m pretty sure Manning&#8217;s XML format would prevent me from even trying &#8211; but I know it&#8217;s possible.</p>
<h3>Fin</h3>
<p>Anyway, long post is long and probably not that interesting to a normal reader. Still, it&#8217;s fascinating for me. The whole process gives me this fuzzy, warm feeling. Made some good progress on Chapter 12 today, and I think I&#8217;m going to go push that to GitHub (and by extension, Twist) right now. Bye!</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Commit it, or else!</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/commit-it-or-else"/>
   <updated>2010-12-09T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/12/commit-it-or-else</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve seen the same question pop up a couple of times now:</p>
<blockquote>
  Should I commit the Gemfile.lock file that Bundler generates?
</blockquote>
<p>Yes. Do it. Do it now if you haven&#8217;t already.</p>

<p>Another common question is:</p>
<blockquote>
  I always get conflicts in my db/schema.rb file, why should I commit that?
</blockquote>
<p>This post answers both.</p>
<h3>"Why should I commit Gemfile.lock?"</h3>
<p>When you run <code>bundle install</code> in your project, Bundler will download and install all the gems and their dependencies and their dependencies&#8217; dependencies (and so on) and then create a <code>Gemfile.lock</code> file based on what it installed.</p>

<p>This file is incredibly important because it lists all the precise versions of everything that your project uses at that point in time. Of course, it&#8217;s up to you to ensure that the project is actually working at this point&#8230; something that you should be doing before you commit the <code>Gemfile</code> <strong>and</strong> the <code>Gemfile.lock</code> files. Whenever somebody else clones this project (say, in a couple of days after your setup) and runs <code>bundle install</code>, they will get the <strong>exact same</strong> versions of the gems. Without <code>Gemfile.lock</code>, dependencies will be re-resolved and versions could have been updated during that time. This can lead to undesired outcomes.</p>

<p>Commit it, or else.</p>
<h3>"Why should I commit schema.rb?</h3>
<p>The <code>db/schema.rb</code> file in Rails plays a very similar role to that of the <code>Gemfile.lock</code>. Its purpose is to provide the schema for the database at the absolute latest point. This allows everybody who&#8217;s working on the project &#8211; regardless of what time they enter the project &#8211; to run <code>rake db:schema:load</code> to get the absolute latest schema.</p>

<p>Now note here that I <strong>don&#8217;t</strong> recommend running <code>rake db:migrate</code> to get the latest database schema. There&#8217;s a couple of reasons why people may think this is a good idea, but let me tell you right now: it isn&#8217;t. If you&#8217;re getting started on a project, use <code>rake db:schema:load</code> to get set up (after, of course, setting up the database).</p>

<p><code>rake db:migrate</code> will run <em>every single damn migration</em> in your project, creating tables in one &#8220;step&#8221; and then destroying them in a future step. This is an utter waste of time. <code>db/schema.rb</code> has the final outcome of it already there for you.</p>

<p>Also, if you&#8217;re using <code>rake db:migrate</code> to insert data into your database: don&#8217;t. Use <code>db/seeds.rb</code> for that.</p>

<p>On a similar train of thought: if you&#8217;re using migrations to execute queries that you can&#8217;t do using Rails helpers, perhaps that&#8217;s not such a good idea either. Think about it: the only way you&#8217;re going to be able to run those again on another machine is by running all the migrations again, which we&#8217;ve just established is a Terrible Idea. What may be less of a Terrible Idea is to have an alternative Rake task such as a <code>db:setup</code> script which runs <code>db:schema:load</code> and then executes those specific queries. Yes, it&#8217;s more files to maintain, but this would stop you from having to run <strong>all</strong> the migrations to get those specific queries to re-run. Migrations shouldn&#8217;t be used to do this kind of low-level activity; it just simply doesn&#8217;t fit.</p>

<p>As for the conflicts in <code>db/schema.rb</code>? You&#8217;re a programmer for crying out loud. Suck it up and deal with it. Or <a href='http://tbaggery.com/2010/10/24/reduce-your-rails-schema-conflicts.html'>code up a solution</a>, at least.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Paths vs Subdomains</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/paths-vs-subdomains"/>
   <updated>2010-11-28T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/paths-vs-subdomains</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier today I put out <a href='http://twitter.com/ryanbigg/status/8747010869956608'>a tweet</a> which asked:</p>
<blockquote>
site.com/account (Github) or account.site.com (Basecamp) style for per-account URLs?
</blockquote>
<p>There were great arguments from both sides in the debate. Tweets like <a href='http://twitter.com/Sutto/status/8799294744170496'>Darcy Laycock's</a> and <a href='http://twitter.com/jms_/status/8770149087707137'>James Ottaway's</a>.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve decided to make it paths for two reasons.</p>
<h3>Easier to test</h3>
<p>Quite simply, paths (http://ticketee.com/account) are much easier to test by booting up <code>rails server</code> than subdomains are. They require no additional configuration by that means and they&#8217;re guaranteed to work on all systems.</p>

<p>Subdomains on the other hand would require use of another tool such as <a href='http://github.com/bjeanes/ghost'>Ghost</a> which would work on Ubuntu and Mac OS X, but not Windows. There is no One True Solution for everybody when it comes to subdomains. Since Rails 3 in Action is intentionally written without discrimination between operating systems, I would prefer this chapter to be no exception to that rule.</p>
<h3>Account sharing</h3>
<p>In the application I am going to be sharing users across accounts. A user that is created on one account, can be gifted access to an alternative account. This would result in an &#8220;open&#8221; system, and I think a path URL would be better for this than a subdomain URL.</p>

<p>Thank you all for your suggestions and the interesting discussions tonight. You&#8217;ve been amazing.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dollars to Documentation</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/dollars-to-documentation"/>
   <updated>2010-11-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/dollars-to-documentation</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I wrote a post called <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/looking-for-sponsors/'>"Looking for Sponsors"</a> where I asked if anyone would be interested in donating to a project where I worked full-time on doing documentation for Rails.</p>

<p>After receiving a great response from it, I&#8217;m <a href='http://pledgie.com/campaigns/14034'>now officially taking donations</a> and <a href='http://docrails.uservoice.com/forums/88055-general'>suggestions on what to document</a>. After all, I want this to be a community-driven event.</p>

<p>I would like to start Monday.</p>

<p>As I say on the Pledgie, I&#8217;ve got some ideas already like finishing the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/initialization.html'>Initialization Internals Guide</a>, but really I&#8217;m leaving this in the hands of the very capable community.</p>

<p>So how about it? <a href='http://pledgie.com/campaigns/14034'>Give me a couple of dollars</a>, and I&#8217;ll give you some great documentation. Deal?</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Looking for Sponsors</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/looking-for-sponsors"/>
   <updated>2010-11-19T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/looking-for-sponsors</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in September I wrote a post called <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/advanced-rails-documentation/'>"Advanced Rails Documentation"</a>, which talked about there being a dearth of advanced Ruby on Rails documentation about the place.</p>

<p>Since then, I&#8217;ve been talking with <strong>a lot</strong> of people in the Ruby world and that&#8217;s changed my opinion of what&#8217;s truly needed. It&#8217;s not so much the <em>advanced</em> documentation that&#8217;s needed, but more on the intermediate parts of Rails such as using application templates / builders, or even an Engines guide for when 3.1 drops. Piotr Sarnacki has been doing some seriously awesome work on those.</p>

<p>Another example, Railscamp was this weekend just gone. It was <strong> bloody great</strong>. During my time spent coding at it, I worked on investigating and documenting the <code>ActionDispatch::Routing::Mapper</code> class, in particular, most of the options for the methods such as <code>namespace</code> and <code>resources</code>. If you see anything wrong with the documentation of these methods, I&#8217;m probably your man to ask.</p>

<p>This is the kind of work that I&#8217;d be doing if I received sponsorship prior to January: working on guides and general documentation for Rails and its ecosystem. If you want examples of my work, you need not look any further than the blogs I&#8217;ve written here, as well as <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>Rails 3 in Action</a>, which is more a beginner-focussed text.</p>

<p>There was a <a href='http://pledgie.com/campaigns/34'>drive just like this back in 2006</a> and that was a resounding success. But back then, Rails was at 1.1.6! Rails has come quite a long way since then, and I think it&#8217;s time that we had some quality, community-sponsored documentation going on. I want to help the community, and I think this is the best way I can be of most use.</p>

<p>The intention of this post is to purely gauge the interest in a project like this. I&#8217;ll write another post during December with a link to a Pledgie (or similar). I&#8217;m more than happy to do it, but a man&#8217;s gotta eat. So my final question is: <strong>would you donate to a project like this, and how much (or what) would you donate?</strong></p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Rails 3 Upgrade</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/the-rails-3-upgrade"/>
   <updated>2010-11-07T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/11/the-rails-3-upgrade</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the interim between GetUp and my-next-big-job I&#8217;ve spent the week at a place in Brisbane called <a href='http://ennova.com.au'>Ennova</a> hanging out with such talented people as <a href='http://twitter.com/ltw_'>Lucas Willett</a> and <a href='http://twitter.com/jasoncodes'>Jason Weathered</a>. During my brief stint I was <s>roped into</s> asked to help out with a Rails 3 upgrade. Here&#8217;s a semi-detailed list of what we did in order to upgrade the existing Rails 2.3.8 application to Rails 3.0.1.</p>
<h3>The Rails 3 Upgrade Handbook</h3><a href='http://railsupgradehandbook.com'>The Rails 3 Upgrade Handbook</a>
<p>I warn you now: this is a huge post (around 4,000 words). I think it contains a lot of good information that could probably help you or someone you know upgrade their application to Rails 3. It was 5 days effort upgrading this application to Rails 3 for two people, but a large majority of that time was spent fixing up the tests for the application as some were not that well-written. Most of the code is good code, though, and that&#8217;s really helpful when you&#8217;re doing something like this. In this post there&#8217;s only going to be mentions of things that are different for this particular application between Rails 2 and Rails 3 and the workflow we went through on each day during this effort.</p>

<p>Our plan of attack was to get at least <code>rails console</code> booting first, then make <code>rails console production</code> boot. Next, the application has both RSpec and test/unit tests as well as Cucumber features, so we chose to get the RSpec tests passing first, then the test/unit tests. If all of these tests passed then most of the Cucumber feature should fall in to place, as they did. The following task would be getting the Cucumber tests passing. During this whole process every time we came across a deprecation warning we would try to fix it.</p>
<h3>Bundler</h3>
<p>Before I came to Ennova they (like all smart / cool / awesome people I know) had already switched their 2.3.8 (I&#8217;m going to keep stressing this point) application over to using Bundler. It worked beautifully! If they hadn&#8217;t done this then we would have to install the &#8220;rails_upgrade&#8221; plugin using this line:</p>

<pre><code>script/plugin install git://github.com/rails/rails_upgrade.git</code></pre>

<p>And then run <code>rake rails:upgrade:gems</code> to switch the <code>config.gem</code> lines in the <em>config/environment(s)/<em>.rb_ files to <code>gem</code> lines in a <em>Gemfile</em>. There&#8217;s other commands that this plugin provides to which we should have used to upgrade our application in retrospect, but I think not using them didn&#8217;t slow us down</em>that* much. <a href='https://github.com/rails/rails_upgrade'>Check out the README here.</a></em></p>

<p>Because they&#8217;d already done this we began the process of upgrading to Rails 3 began with this line in the <em>Gemfile</em>:</p>
<pre>
  gem 'rails', '3.0.1'
</pre>
<p>Then we needed to run <code>bundle install</code> and then we were on our way.</p>
<h3>Monday</h3><strong>Partner: Lucas Willet</strong>
<p>Most of the upgrade process is a matter of &#8220;following the bouncing ball&#8221;. If we saw a deprecation warning, generally speaking it was explanatory enough that we were able to understand what it meant and then go about fixing it. The notes beneath are for those issues which were <em>not</em> purely deprecation warnings, but &#8220;gotchas&#8221;.</p>

<p>To &#8220;upgrade&#8221; the application, we begun by ensuring that everything was committed to a branch and that the application was stable. This application is a well-tested application (not 100% coverage, but getting there) and we assumed that if all the tests were passing on the 2.x version of the application then the goal to ensure that the Rails 3 application was upgraded is that all the tests should be passing too. If the application had any failing tests it would be priority #1 to fix these up before going through with the upgrade.</p>

<p>The application uses Git for version control so we checked out a new branch called &#8220;rails-3&#8221; and began our work. The next command we had to use was the <code>rails new .</code> from within the application itself which runs the Rails application generator on the current directory. This is where you have to be really careful that it doesn&#8217;t override things such as the <em>app/controllers/application.rb</em> file. If you&#8217;ve got version control then it&#8217;s quite easy to check out this file, but if you miss it then it&#8217;s difficult (as in, you&#8217;d have to generate another application and copy over the important bits) of a file if you press the wrong key during this part. Be very careful.</p>

<p>Our first test was to see if we could get <code>rails console production</code> running which would mean that the application was at least booting in production mode, then we would move on to getting the tests to pass. the &#8220;production&#8221; environment is very similar to the &#8220;test&#8221; environment and although we <em>could</em> have used the &#8220;test&#8221; environment, we wanted to make sure that all the production-environment code was running. When we ran this command, it bombed as expected. <strong>No upgrade is smooth.</strong></p>

<p>The first couple of errors we encountered we for the <code>acts_as_archive</code> and <code>searchlogic</code> gems. I don&#8217;t have the errors to hand right now, but they were show-stoppers. Quite a lot of the errors we encountered were because we were using older versions of gems, or that the gems had not been updated on their &#8220;canonical&#8221; repositories so we had to find forks. These were both this kind of error.</p>

<p><code>acts_as_archive</code> was easy enough to upgrade, we found <a href='http://github.com/xxx/acts_as_archive'>a fork by xxx</a> for it and pointed our Gemfile at that. We found out that the <em>gemspec</em> wasn&#8217;t quite right (it referenced a non-existant <code>rails</code> directory) and so we committed a patch to make it stop displaying a warning for it and xxx was kind enough to merge it.</p>

<p>Then there was Searchlogic. What a gigantic clusterfuck of code. I don&#8217;t blame him for writing such terrible code, it was written before ARel existed and ARel does effectively most of what Searchlogic does anyway. I&#8217;m sure <a href='http://github.com/binarylogic'>binarylogic</a> has the best intentions at heart, but his code is really fucking confusing for me. We also found a <a href='http://github.com/railsdog/searchlogic'>Rails 3 compatible fork of Searchlogic by railsdog</a> and it worked for most cases. We ended up chucking it out and writing our own scopes using ARel (which, if at all possible, has now made me <strong>more</strong> in love with Aaron Patterson), including a custom <a href='https://gist.github.com/663752'>module of our (Jason and myself) own called `WildcardSearch`</a>. This allows us to search for keywords in specific fields of the table we&#8217;re looking up in, and allows us to also do queries on associated records too. Check out the code, it&#8217;s great stuff.</p>

<p>In the application there was a <em>config/preinitializer.rb</em> which was being used for setting up Bundler, as well as defining constants or changing things such as the default date formatting in the application. For Rails 2.3.8, you need the <em>config/preinitializer.rb</em> to load Bundler, but because we upgraded to Rails 3 this part of the file was now redundant&#8230; but where would you put the constants / settings? We decided it would be best to move them into an initializer, which involved quite simply creating a new file at <em>config/initializers/default.rb</em> and moving the code across. Generally speaking, any code that sets up your application&#8217;s environment should now be placed in <em>config/initializers</em>, not <em>lib</em>.</p>

<p>Next up, in <em>config/environments/production.rb</em> we set the <code>config.active_support.deprecation</code> to <code>:notify</code> so that when the application was running in production mode (like when we were running <code>rails console production</code>) it would show us the deprecation warnings in the console rather than hiding them. We also set this same setting to <code>:stderr</code> in the <em>config/environments/test.rb</em> and <em>config/environments/development.rb</em> files. Also in these files there was reference to an old setting called <code>consider_all_requests_local</code>, which we removed reference to.</p>

<p>The first deprecation warning that came up when <code>rails console production</code> decided it wanted to start booting our application was that the syntax in our routes file was deprecated. This was because we were using the deprecated mapper, which in simple terms meaning that our routes went like this:</p>

<pre><code>ActionController::Routing::Routes.draw do |map|
  map.root :controller =&gt; &quot;welcome&quot;, :action =&gt; &quot;index&quot;</code></pre>

<p>When they should be something like this:</p>

<pre><code>Rails.application.routes.draw do
  root :to =&gt; &quot;welcome#index&quot;</code></pre>

<p>Ahh, much better! This is where we stuffed up, we should have run the <code>rake rails:upgrade:routes</code> command <em>before</em> we ran <code>rails new .</code> because the rails upgrade plugin only works on a Rails 2 application. We spent a couple of minutes going through this file fixing up all the lines in this file to use their new syntax. Whilst it&#8217;s handy to know how each of the methods map across between Rails 2 and 3, it&#8217;s also good to know that if you don&#8217;t know what a route <em>should</em> be in Rails 3 that you can reference the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/routing.html'>Routing Guide</a>. The current (as-of-writing) gem version for <em>declarative_authorization</em> is 0.5 and it uses this old, deprecated routing syntax too. Thankfully sttfn has updated his gem like all good gem authors <em>should</em>, and we were able to load the gem straight from GitHub with this line:</p>

<pre><code>gem &#39;declarative_authorization&#39;, :git =&gt; &quot;git://github.com/stffn/declarative_authorization&quot;</code></pre>

<p>The next warnings when running <code>rails console production</code> was that we were using <code>named_scope</code> when in Rails 3 the correct method is simply <code>scope</code>. We did a find-and-replace to fix these up, only to run <code>rails console</code> and to find out that <code>authlogic</code> this time was the one throwing the remaining warnings. I&#8217;d already done an upgrade at GetUp from Rails 2 to Rails 3 and because binarylogic is inattentive of his gems I went about doing an upgrade for it to make it work with Rails 3, resulting in <a href='http://github.com/radar/authlogic'>my fork of authlogic</a> which should have all the deprecation warnings fixed.</p>

<p>More ActiveRecord deprecations were next, with a couple of callbacks in our application defined like this:</p>

<pre><code>def after_update
  # do something
end</code></pre>

<p>Other callbacks like <code>before_create</code> and <code>after_create</code> existed too. Rather than defining the callback methods like this, the correct way in Rails 3 to define these is to define them as methods (private ones for bonus points) and then use the callback to call them, like this:</p>

<pre><code>after_update :do_something

def do_something
  something.do!
end</code></pre>

<p>It&#8217;s best practice to define the callbacks like this because you may have multiple callbacks you want to run after a record has been updated, or created or whatever.</p>

<p>It was after this that our <code>rails console production</code> booted with no errors. Great! The application has RSpec and test/unit tests, and I&#8217;m very partial to RSpec so we tried running it and it bombed too. We bumped the version number of <code>rspec-rails</code> up to 2.0.1 in the <em>Gemfile</em>, ran <code>bundle install</code> again and then tried running the tests. They failed because of this error:</p>

<pre><code>no such file to load -- spec</code></pre>

<p>We had to change the requires in <em>spec/spec_helper.rb</em> from this:</p>

<pre><code>require &#39;spec/autorun&#39;
require &#39;spec/rails&#39;
require &#39;spec&#39;</code></pre>

<p>To this:</p>

<pre><code>require &#39;rspec/autorun&#39;
require &#39;rspec/rails&#39;
require &#39;rspec&#39;</code></pre>

<p>Also in this file, the <code>Spec::Runner</code> constant doesn&#8217;t exist, and this is used for this line further down in the file:</p>

<pre><code>Spec::Runner.configure do |config|
   ...
end</code></pre>

<p>RSpec is now configured using the <code>RSpec</code> constant, so the above lines are now:</p>

<pre><code>RSpec.configure do |config|
  ...
end</code></pre>

<p>At this point RSpec was launching and we were informed of our next deprecation warning: the <code>cache_template_loading</code> setting for the application configuration (ours was in <em>config/environments/test.rb</em>) has been deprecated, and so we had to remove it. After this our specs were at least running (but not all passing), and so we decided we&#8217;d come back to them after we attempted to get the test/unit tests to pass. Just like <code>rails console</code> and the RSpec tests before them, they bombed too.</p>

<p>This time it was due to this error:</p>

<pre><code>no such file to load -- test_help</code></pre>

<p>To be honest, I don&#8217;t use test/unit to test Rails applications, I just hate it. I was pairing with Lucas on the application and he&#8217;d been brought up to only ever use RSpec and Cucumber, so he was just following my lead on this one. Then I made a bad mistake: <strong>I removed the test_help line</strong>.</p>
<small>We found out a few days later that this file is actually now at `rails/test_help`. This file is incredibly important for transactions in tests and it wasn't until Wednesday when we fixed this problem. Don't make the same mistake as us, it's important!</small>
<p>In quite a lot of our test/unit tests we had this line:</p>

<pre><code>include ActionController::Assertions::SelectorAssertions</code></pre>

<p>This module has now been moved into Action Dispatch and so the correct <code>include</code> is this:</p>

<pre><code>include ActionDispatch::Assertions::SelectorAssertions</code></pre>

<p>The rest of Monday was spent working on writing the <code>WildcardSearch</code> module and getting stuck on a little bug with it.</p>
<h3>Tuesday</h3><strong>Partner: Jason</strong>
<p>This was the first day that I got to pair with <a href='http://twitter.com/jasoncodes'>Jason Weathered (@jasoncodes)</a> and we carried on the good work that Lucas and I did the day before. Jason&#8217;s been doing Rails for about a year now but is scarily on or very near my level. Dude is amazing.</p>

<p>The first problem we fixed on Tuesday was that <code>rake spec</code> was running, but not returning anything. It turns out that it this is because we had <code>rspec-rails</code> in the <code>:test</code> group which means that its rake tasks were only being loaded in the <code>test</code> environment, where by running <code>rake spec</code> we need them to exist in the <code>:development</code> group. Moving this gem into a group block like this:</p>

<pre><code>group :development, :test do 
  gem &#39;rspec-rails&#39;, &#39;2.0.1&#39;
end</code></pre>

<p>This makes RSpec&#8217;s rake tasks available in the <code>development</code> environment so we were able to run <code>rake spec.</code> All of Tuesday was spent trying to get the RSpec tests to pass once again.</p>

<p>With the forked version of Searchlogic we were using, our <code>*_like_any</code> methods like the one used in this method:</p>

<pre><code>def text_contains(text)
  name_or_description_or_optional_originator_username_or_status_like_any
end</code></pre>

<p>Just weren&#8217;t working. The methods were apparently undefined. The intention of this method is to find an Event with a name or description containing keywords. Let&#8217;s assume that <code>text</code> in this context is &#8220;foo bar&#8221;, the query the <code>like_any</code> method uses here will look up an <code>Event</code> record which has a name containing either foo <em>OR</em> bar, or a description containing either foo <em>OR</em> bar, or a related user who&#8217;s username contains either foo <em>OR</em> bar. It&#8217;s a messy query, and this Searchlogic method generated it for us. I&#8217;m not going to post the mess here. We replaced this method with v1 of our <code>WildcardSearch</code> module, the end-result (on Thursday) looking like this:</p>

<pre><code>def text_contains(text)
  self.includes(:originator).wildcard_search(:name, :description, { :originator =&gt; :username })
end</code></pre>

<p>We use <code>includes</code> here and pass it an association name. ARel&#8217;s really smart and will know if we use the association name here what table to join. Even better than that, when we use a <code>where</code> later on in that same query, it will use a <code>LEFT OUTER JOIN</code> to join that table and run the query on the <code>events</code> and <code>users</code> tables. ARel is extremely capable of doing what Searchlogic did, it&#8217;s Rails 3 compatible and it&#8217;s supported by somebody who&#8217;s fairly active in the community: Aaron Patterson. It was about this moment where we decided to scrap all usage of Searchlogic in our application favour of ARel. After this replacement, quite a few of our failing specs were passing.</p>

<p>A large majority of this day was spent cherry-picking off failing specs. The first of these was that our tests making sure the validations were in place were checking that the error message contains a string:</p>

<pre><code>thing.errors[:user_id].should == &quot;has already been taken&quot;</code></pre>

<p>When in Rails 3, errors<span>:attribute</span> now returns an <code>Array</code>. The Rails 3 correct version of this is:</p>

<pre><code>thing.errors[:user_id].should == [&quot;has already been taken&quot;]</code></pre>

<p>Fixing this fixed up even more of our specs, but we still had work to go. During the running of our specs we encountered a deprecation warning with our mailer:</p>

<pre><code>Notifier.deliver_confirmation_instructions is deprecated, use Notifier.confirmation_instructions.deliver instead.</code></pre>

<p>We fixed this up nice and quickly and looked through the application for <code>deliver_</code> and fixed those deprecations up too. Personally I prefer to use the <code>deliver!</code> alias method as a &#8220;destructive&#8221; / &#8220;undoable&#8221; method.</p>

<p>The next issue we came across was to do with a little change between Rails 2 and 3 in regards to partial rendering. It had to do with a line like this:</p>

<pre><code>render :partial =&gt; &quot;some/partial&quot;, :collection =&gt; @things</code></pre>

<p>In Rails 2, when you pass the <code>:collection</code> option to <code>render</code> like this, each of the objects are passed to the partial as <code>object</code>. In Rails 3, this changes to be the name of the partial itself mainly because now you can do things like this:</p>

<pre><code>render @things</code></pre>

<p>Let&#8217;s assume for the time being that the <code>@things</code> variable is a collection of <code>Thing</code> objects. When you call <code>render @things</code> this will render, by default, the partial at <em>app/views/things/_things.html.erb</em>. The objects of the collection are then passed through as the local variable <code>thing</code>. Our problem was that we were using the Rails 2 line, and so Rails 3 was assuming that we wanted the variables still called after the partial. To give the variables the right name we use lines like this:</p>

<pre><code>render :partial =&gt; &quot;some/partial&quot;, :collection =&gt; @things, :as =&gt; :other_thing</code></pre>

<p>Now the objects will be available in the partial as <code>other_thing</code>. This fixed most of the view breakages, although we had another big one coming up.</p>

<p>That was the <code>nested_layouts</code> gem which is no longer compatible with Rails 3. To fix this, we used <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/layouts_and_rendering.html#using-nested-layouts'>this section</a> from the bottom of the Layouts and Rendering guide for Rails 3. I think this is a much more elegant solution to the <code>nested_layouts</code> hackery.</p>

<p>After fixing <em>that</em> test, the next problem was that one of our files in <em>lib</em> was not being loaded. This is because in Rails 2 the files in <em>lib</em> are autoloaded, where in Rails 3 you must manually require them. Or at least you would if you didn&#8217;t have this option in <em>config/application.rb</em>:</p>

<pre><code>config.load_paths += %W( #{config.root}/lib )</code></pre>

<p>If you wanted to add more directories to be autoloaded just add them to this array. With this small change we fixed some more &#8220;broken&#8221; tests.</p>

<p>The next problem was that we were getting this error in some of our views:</p>

<pre><code>undefined local variable or method `form_remote_tag&#39;</code></pre>

<p>In Rails 2 the <code>form_remote_tag</code> and related methods have been moved out into a plugin called <code>prototype_legacy_helper</code>. We installed this plugin using this command:</p>

<pre><code>rails plugin:install git://github.com/rails/prototype_legacy_helper</code></pre>

<p>After installing this plugin our tests were <em>still</em> failing. We later found out that it was a bug with <code>prototype_legacy_helper</code> itself so I asked Jos Valim (the Rails core member) who maintains it. He replied &#8220;I don&#8217;t know&#8221;. Uh oh. So Jason and I fixed the bug and in doing so I gained commit rights to the project. Therefore I suppose I&#8217;m now the maintainer of it. If you want a bug fixed in it send in a patch and I&#8217;ll apply it.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s how we wrapped up Tuesday.</p>
<h3>Wednesday</h3><strong>Partner: Jason</strong>
<p>Jason and I were pairing on Wednesday too. By this point, we&#8217;d fixed the major issues with the application and were just going through the deprecation warnings in the application. A lot of the changes for this day were fixing deprecation warnings in the application, and so this day may seem like we didn&#8217;t do much, but we did quite a bit.</p>

<p>One of the major changes was that now any helper that outputs something in a view uses the <code>&lt;%=</code> ERB tag, rather than <code>&lt;%</code>. The latter&#8217;s going to be deprecated in Rails 3.1 so it&#8217;s best that we switch this over. Most of this happened on the <code>form_for</code>, but we had a couple of <code>content_tag</code>s that were doing it too.</p>

<p>We started off the day by realising that we didn&#8217;t need the <em>config/environments/cucumber.rb</em> file any more, Cucumber now runs within the &#8220;test&#8221; environment rather than its own special &#8220;cucumber&#8221; environment. This also means that we could remove the <code>cucumber</code> key from <em>config/database.yml</em> as that database setting is never used.</p>

<p>A couple of our functional tests had referenced a constant &#8211; <code>ActionController::TestUploadedFile</code> &#8211; which is now available in Rack instead as <code>Rack::Test::UploadedFile</code>. There was also some tests referring to fixtures which we converted over to using Factory Girl&#8217;s factories.</p>

<p>We also had a plugin which had its <em>tasks</em> folder in the root of the directory, where Rails 3 expects it to be in <em>lib/tasks</em>. It was a plugin of our own making so we moved this folder into its proper spot.</p>

<p>The application Sass extensively, so when we tried the application through <code>rails server</code>, it created new files at <em>public/stylesheets</em> for the parsed Sass stylesheets. This is incorrect, as the Hassle gem we had installed should have been putting them into a <em>tmp</em> folder and reading it from there because this application is deployed on Heroku. To fix this, we changed the <code>gem</code> specification of hassle in our <em>Gemfile</em> to this:</p>

<pre><code>gem &#39;hassle&#39;, &#39;0.0.1&#39;, :git =&gt; &#39;git://github.com/fphilipe/hassle.git&#39;</code></pre>

<p>Next, we created an initializer to load Hassle in as a middleware, called <em>config/initializers/hassle.rb</em>:</p>

<pre><code>Rails.configuration.middleware.use Hassle</code></pre>

<p>With fphilipe&#8217;s fork of <code>hassle</code>, we were able to get the stylesheets to go in the correct directory.</p>

<p>At the end of Wednesday, Jason and I came across a problem where a <code>flash[:notice]</code> was seemingly being lost and we spent the last half-an-hour trying to figure out why, to no avail.</p>
<h3>Thursday</h3><strong>Partner: Lucas</strong>
<p>On Thursday on the way in I talked to Lucas about Wednesday night&#8217;s problem and suggested it could be a double redirect as I had seen it happen before on an application. Turns out that was the problem, and we used <code>flash.keep</code> to keep the flash for the next request. With this final little change, all the test/unit tests, functionals and RSpec tests were passing. Time to get the Cucumber features to pass.</p>

<p>One of the little minor-changes-that-breaks-everything was that in Rails 2 the submit button for a form, if not given an argument, defaulted to &#8220;Save changes&#8221;. In Rails 3, this now defaults to either &#8220;Create <span>Object</span>&#8221; where <span>Object</span> is the class name of the form&#8217;s object, or &#8220;Update <span>Object</span>&#8221;. The view inspects the model object it&#8217;s given to determine what the button should display! I think this is much better, but it just about broke The Everything. We went through the features and did a manual find-and-replace for all these occurrences and fixed them up.</p>

<p>Next, we had a helper which was outputting HTML as a string. This is problematic because in Rails 3, all HTML-as-a-string is marked as unsafe, and is escaped. To fix this we used <code>html_safe</code> on the return value of this helper. There was also another helper in this file which we fixed up a little later on too.</p>

<p>The next deprecation warning we came across wasn&#8217;t to do with Rails, but Capybara. It was this:</p>

<pre><code>DEPRECATED: #click is deprecated, please use #click_link_or_button instead</code></pre>

<p>We found the offending step and changed it to use this new method.</p>

<p>It was at about this point that we decided to scrap Searchlogic. On our <code>Person</code> model we had a boolean field called <code>active</code> which Searchlogic should have been defining a scope much like this for:</p>

<pre><code>scope :active, where(:active =&gt; true)</code></pre>

<p>Sadly, this wasn&#8217;t working. My suspicion was that it was defining it something like this:</p>

<pre><code>scope :active, where(:active =&gt; &#39;t&#39;)</code></pre>

<p>or</p>

<pre><code>scope :active, where(:active =&gt; &#39;true&#39;)</code></pre>

<p>As I stated before, Searchlogic is a clusterfuck of a codebase and so I didn&#8217;t really want go hunting in there. I also said before that ARel does exactly what Searchlogic did, so we scrapped Searchlogic. A quick run of the RSpec tests picked up any occurrences where we removed Something Important and we re-implemented the scopes with ARel. Probably took us all of 10 minutes.</p>

<p>In some custom code we had this:</p>

<pre><code>some_association.scoped(:include =&gt; :children)</code></pre>

<p>It took me a little while before I realised that you can just use ARel for this too:</p>

<pre><code>some_association.includes(:children)</code></pre>

<p>It was just one of those way-too-obvious fixes that you overlook initially and then gape in awe when you write it.</p>
<h3>Friday</h3><strong>Partner: Jason</strong>
<p>The final day!</p>

<p>We had some features that used the <code>WildcardSearch</code> module that were failing, even though we were <em>positive</em> it was correct. Turns out it wasn&#8217;t case-insensitive! Also turns out that Rails 3.0.1 (well, actually the version of ARel that <em>comes with</em> Rails 3.0.1), doesn&#8217;t support case-insensitive matching with the <em>matches</em> method. Thankfully there&#8217;s a smart-cookie out there who&#8217;s written <a href='https://rails.lighthouseapp.com/projects/8994/tickets/3174-add-support-for-postgresql-citext-column-type'>a beautiful patch</a> for it, <strong>but it only works with PostgreSQL</strong>. That&#8217;s fine, we&#8217;re smart so we use PostgreSQL. We used the patch&#8217;s code in an initializer and it worked flawlessly.</p>

<p>During the running of our tests, we used <code>Then show me the page</code> <strong>a lot</strong>. This resulted in lots of <em>capybara-[timestamp]</em> files in the root directory. To fix this little problem, we put this code in our <em>features/support/app.rb</em> file:</p>

<pre><code>Capybara.save_and_open_page_path = Rails.root + &#39;tmp&#39;</code></pre>

<p>All fixed!</p>

<p>One of our actions returned two formats: a <code>html</code> version and a <code>pdf</code> format. In the <code>pdf</code> <code>respond_to</code> block the code looked like this:</p>

<pre><code>@template.template_format = :html
kit = PDFKit.new(render_to_string)</code></pre>

<p>It turns out that <code>@template</code> is no longer an accessible-from-the-controller variable. Who&#8217;d have thunk it? To work around this problem, we had to use the (undocumented! grr) <code>:action</code> option for <code>render_to_string</code>, changing the final line to this:</p>

<pre><code>kit = PDFKit.new(render_to_string(:action =&gt; &#39;print.html.haml&#39;))</code></pre>

<p>We simply wanted the <code>html</code> version of this template, where as this code was trying to render the <code>print.pdf.erb</code> template which simply didn&#8217;t exist.</p>

<p>The next issue was that we were using <code>find_or_create_by*</code> in a step like this:</p>

<pre><code>role = @project.roles.find_or_create_by_name(role_name, :category =&gt; category)</code></pre>

<p>This syntax isn&#8217;t supported in Rails 3 (it thinks that <code>:category</code> is a key like <code>:joins</code> or <code>:includes</code>) and so we had to change it to the way-more-verbose this:</p>

<pre><code>role = @project.roles.find_by_name(role_name) || @project.roles.create!(:name =&gt; role_name, :category =&gt; category)</code></pre>

<p>That was the final Rails 3-caused issue that we came across on Friday, and by 4pm we had all the Cucumber features, RSpec specs, and test/unit tests all passing. Everything worked.</p>
<h3>So now what?</h3>
<p>Well, Ennova&#8217;s not going to deploy this application directly to production just yet. I&#8217;d say they should give it a week on staging so that one of the business guys can go through the application and make sure it&#8217;s working as intended. The application isn&#8217;t <em>completely</em> covered in tests, so there&#8217;s bound to be something we missed out. For the most part though, it&#8217;s a fully-functional Rails 3 application working nearly-exactly like it did in Rails 2.</p>

<p>A lot of the upgrading work was done on Monday and Tuesday, with quite a large majority of the remaining time spent just fixing deprecation warnings in our application or making the tests better. All in all, I think it went very well.</p>

<p>I hope this helps somebody out there get up the nerve to upgrade their application to Rails 3. It&#8217;s stable, it&#8217;s proven to work (Gemcutter, for instance, runs Rails 3) and it&#8217;s awesome. Also, with all <a href='http://edgeguides.rubyonrails.org/3_0_release_notes.html'>the new features in Rails 3</a>, how can you resist?</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gone from GetUp</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/gone-from-getup"/>
   <updated>2010-10-30T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/gone-from-getup</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was my last day at GetUp. I&#8217;m moving on to bigger and better things now.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;ve been <a href='http://twitter.com/ryanbigg'>following me on Twitter</a> you would have been able to work out by the hints that I&#8217;ve been dropping all week that this was the case. If you didn&#8217;t work it out from the hints then <a href='http://twitter.com/#!/ryanbigg/status/29062245881'>one of last night's messages</a> should have spelled it out clearly enough.</p>

<p>During my time there, I was training up the ex-PHP developers in the ways of Ruby on Rails whilst developing the new version of GetUp&#8217;s website. This is definitely the kind of work that I want to do for as long as I&#8217;m able, it&#8217;s been a blast.</p>

<p>There are many reasons why I&#8217;m leaving the organisation and some of them cannot be made public. What can be made public is that last Thursday changed everything.</p>

<p>I received news early that morning that a very good UK friend of mine, (Angus / Fares Yusuf) Donaldson, had passed away 6 days prior. We had met online a couple of years back, hanging out in #rubyonrails, #offrails and more recently #railsbridge together. It was until March this year when I was on my way to Scotland that we met in person, staying in Heathrow Airport for 7 hours during an epic layover between flights. I kept telling Angus that my flight was at 2:30pm and he kept saying it was fine. By the time Angus brought me to the correct terminal, the flight had already gone through final boarding and I hadn&#8217;t even checked in yet! Angus thought that the <em>check-in</em> time was the one I was saying, NOT the flight departure time. Whilst I was mildly panicking, he sweet-talked an airhostess and got me on the next available flight. I&#8217;ll miss him quite a lot. It made me feel mortal. If the indestructible Angus could die, then I could too.</p>

<p>Later on that morning the other friend I caught up with in the UK, Sam Elliott, sent me a DM about a job that I may be interested in. I looked into it and contacted the people offering it, but then had to leave for work. Was still in a shocked/dazed state when I arrived, I don&#8217;t remember much. At about 10am I had a chat to the company but I wasn&#8217;t able to offer my help because I wasn&#8217;t sure if my contract was going to end the following week or not.</p>

<p>This was one of the things about GetUp and my contract. I never received a paper copy until about 6 months in. During the whole time I was there, my contract was extended by about a month per time, going from end of May to end of June, to end of July, to end of October. These discussions happened usually less than 1 week before the contract expired. Obviously there was still work to do, but I had no hint if the contract was going to still be extended or not. I would have preferred greater notice.</p>

<p>On Thursday night I got some bad news: they were going to be letting two of my team go, James and Charles. I read it as they were &#8220;thinking&#8221; of doing it, but the following Monday found out it was a definite. On Monday afternoon, each of the Online team had one-on-ones with Daryl and Simon with Charles and then James going first. I asked James what they asked him and he showed me a letter with &#8220;Redundancy&#8221; as the header. To be perfectly honest, I was furious at this stage. They were letting the two full-time people on the team who were getting decent at Rails go. I calmed down, sat through my one-on-one without leaping the desk and smashing Simon&#8217;s stupid face into a bloody pulp, went home, and cried.</p>

<p>I talked with a lot of people that night. That was the theme over the next few days as well, just pure talking. Voice chats, text messages, Skype chats&#8230; it was just so much talking. The company I spoke to on Thursday asked me again on Tuesday morning if I&#8217;d still be interested and I basically said &#8220;yes, I&#8217;m very much interested and leaning that way now, but I have to talk to my boss&#8221;. So on Tuesday morning I spoke with Daryl who sympathised with my anger, but wished that I could stay on 6 more weeks. I said that I would have to speak with the other company again.</p>

<p>Wednesday morning, that&#8217;s what happened. They said they needed somebody right away and if they couldn&#8217;t get me, then they&#8217;d have to move on. If I didn&#8217;t leave GetUp, I could have potentially missed out on this fabulous opportunity. I told Daryl the bad news Wednesday morning and he said he was disappointed but agreed that I had to do what was best for me. At the end of the week, I would be leaving GetUp and moving on.</p>

<p>The other company was really happy when I told them late Wednesday morning, and so was I. It&#8217;s something that I&#8217;ve wanted to do for quite a long time and I really think it&#8217;ll benefit the community in a great way. Sorry for being so cryptic about the details, just there&#8217;s very little that I&#8217;m able to share right now.</p>

<p>Thursday and Friday was handover with Alex (contractor) and Francois (full-timer). I wish them the best of luck in developing and delivering v3. On Friday at the team meeting I got given a great well wishes card from the team as well as an awesome satchel bag for my laptop that doesn&#8217;t look as dodgy as a backpack.</p>

<p>On Sunday, my contract expires. After that, I&#8217;m going to be spending two weeks in Brisbane, one of them working for a company up there doing a Rails 3 upgrade work and some pairing with their team and then the following week I begin my contract at this new job. It&#8217;s a remote contract so I&#8217;ll probably just be desk-hopping around the place doing the work. I&#8217;d like to not stay in the house the whole time. The weekend after that is Railscamp, which I&#8217;m really looking forward to.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m still going to be writing Rails 3 in Action during this new contract. We&#8217;re hoping to have a new release out Real Soon Now(tm), as soon as I get some time to speak with Yehuda about the latest major review comments. It should contain chapters 1-10 with 11 coming Real Soon After(tm).</p>

<p>The future&#8217;s looking good. See you there.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Writing isn't all rainbows</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/writing-isnt-all-rainbows"/>
   <updated>2010-10-19T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/writing-isnt-all-rainbows</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There, I said it and I&#8217;ll say it again.</p>

<p>Writing isn&#8217;t all rainbows.</p>

<p>What do I mean by this? Put simply: it&#8217;s not an enjoyable process all of the time. It has its moments, both good and bad. Right now you may be able to tell I&#8217;m having a bad one. I should be writing Rails 3 in Action, but instead I&#8217;m writing this post.</p>

<p>As a famous author once said: &#8220;Writing is like taking a shit. Don&#8217;t if you don&#8217;t <strong>have</strong> to.&#8221;. So I&#8217;m not writing tonight. I am simply not in the mood for it, and to be perfectly honest I am feeling a lot burned out tonight. I am human too.</p>

<p>Writing Rails 3 in Action is difficult. I have to stay on top of the gem changes (such as rspec and rails, which should now be stable) and know what is the &#8220;accepted best practice&#8221; of how to do something. I then have to explain that in exceptional detail so that people get it on their first read and know what I&#8217;m thinking at this point. If a reader gets lost, then I have failed.</p>

<p>I do most of my writing on the weekends, since I am working full time at GetUp. Chapter 8 took me almost a month to complete because it was a very complex chapter that had a lot going on all at once. I eventually re-wrote it and people have been saying it&#8217;s much better. Relief. Chapter 10 took me a little over a week. Chapter 11 should be completed this weekend (its third weekend).</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re thinking of writing a book ask yourself one question: What makes yours unique? I&#8217;m trying to make Rails 3 in Action unique by using Cucumber, RSpec, Rails and all the other gems we use to build a full-featured application throughout the entire book. I hope this is unique enough for the readers.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not writing this for the money. Being honest, the advances I&#8217;ve been receiving wouldn&#8217;t even fund my rent for the time it took to write the part I&#8217;m being paid for, let alone all the other fun things you have to pay for in life. There is no way I can live on just the money from the book advances, so I work. Working what is basically super-full-time takes its toll on a person after a while, and I get a little down.</p>

<p>However, when you work at a job where there&#8217;s interesting challenges to solve and good people to work with, then that isn&#8217;t as much of a drag as some would think. GetUp&#8217;s like that, and I&#8217;m thankful for that. I can go home at the end of the day feeling &#8220;accomplished&#8221; and thinking &#8220;what can I accomplish on the book tonight?&#8221;. Those kinds of nights I&#8217;ll bash out a section or two. Tonight is not one of those nights, for reasons I won&#8217;t go into right now.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not writing the book for the money. I&#8217;m not writing it for the fame (got enough, thanks). I&#8217;m writing it because when a person tweets about it or posts to the forum and uses phrases like &#8220;awesome!&#8221; and &#8220;thanks for this, I really love what you&#8217;ve done!&#8221;&#8230;</p>

<p>That&#8217;s the &#8220;rainbows&#8221; I live for. That&#8217;s what I write for.</p>

<p>Thanks for your support so far. It makes nights like this all that more tolerable.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Lighthouse has problems, but they're fixing them</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/lighthouse-has-problems-but-theyre-fixing-them"/>
   <updated>2010-10-11T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/lighthouse-has-problems-but-theyre-fixing-them</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I wrote my <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/lighthouse-has-problems/'>Lighthouse has problems</a> post last week, I was contacted by ENTP who asked to speak to me regarding some clarifications, and now I&#8217;ve finally gotten around to posting them.</p>

<p>Firstly: ENTP is working on a major upgrade of Lighthouse. They <a href='http://help.lighthouseapp.com/discussions/problems/1791-spammers-taking-over'>plan on fixing the spam issue </a>and will have trusted and untrusted user accounts, where trusted users can change the title and tags of a ticket. They will also implement rate limiting which will be a way to detect the spammers current tactics on LH. This fixes points #2 and #4 of my post.</p>

<p>Secondly: there&#8217;s now less tickets for Rails itself with the <a href='https://rails.lighthouseapp.com/projects/8994-ruby-on-rails/tickets/bins/5837'>"Open Tickets"</a> currently hovering around 753. This is because of the wonderful team of Lighthouse volunteers including David Trasbo, Rohit Arondekar who have been marking old tickets as stale and replying to those which need patches. If you have a ticket which you&#8217;d like some eyes on, assign it to one of us and we&#8217;ll take a peek.</p>

<p>Thirdly: I wrote <a href='http://gist.github.com/617963'>a Mechanize script</a> to revert / delete the spam comments, which will stave off the problem until ENTP can get around to fixing their system. Myself and a couple of other volunteers run this whenever spammers are detected. Seems to do the trick quite nicely, but the code is ugly as all hell.</p>

<p>I have to play the devil&#8217;s advocate here: Lighthouse doesn&#8217;t suck, entirely. It&#8217;s a bit rough around the edges but it&#8217;s no Trac. Remember Trac? Good times were had, and spam was a problem back then. It&#8217;s a tricky problem to solve and I hope that the Lighthouse guys can actually do some serious work on it, maybe even implement a <em>proper</em> spam filter, such as Akismet, but nothing is perfect.</p>

<p>Lighthouse is serving us perfectly fine right now, it&#8217;s just a little cluttered. We&#8217;re working on that, and we&#8217;d like your help. If you could spend some of your time this week going through the <a href='https://rails.lighthouseapp.com/projects/8994-ruby-on-rails/tickets/bins/5837'>"Open Tickets"</a> and assigning old ones to one of either Rohit, David or myself, we&#8217;ll get right round to closing them up.</p>

<p>I&#8217;d like to see it below 700 by the end of next weekend.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Lighthouse has problems</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/lighthouse-has-problems"/>
   <updated>2010-10-06T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/lighthouse-has-problems</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once again, the Rails lighthouse is chockas. 944 open tickets as of this post.</p>

<p>That is disgraceful. I wrote how I felt back in April, and now I am just sad, not angry.</p>

<p>Nobody is willing to dedicate the time required to go through and play gatekeeper between these tickets and the core team, and so there is only a dribble of tickets actually being looked at / dealt with. Sure, we can have bugmashes every &#8220;x&#8221; &#8220;y&#8221;, but they only do so much. We need a continued effort to bring this number down and keep it down, but it&#8217;s not for the financial benefit of everyone, so nobody&#8217;s going to do it.</p>

<p>Besides that, Lighthouse has some quite serious issues itself. The sheer fact that I have to use an ordered list to outline the problems shows the extreme side of this situation.</p>
<ol>
  <li>There's no way for a project "admin" to completely delete / ban a user. For instance if I want to delete a <a href='https://rails.lighthouseapp.com/users/118614'>spamming fucktard</a> like this guy, I can't.</li>
  <li>There is no spam protection. If a user posts two comments within the space of a minute they should be prompted with a captcha. This will stop the bot spam, at least. Manual spam can be dealt with by fixing point #1.</li>
  <li>If I don't want to delete a user, but I want to delete <strong>some</strong> of their comments, I can't do that either.</li>
  <li>Normal users can change the title of a ticket <strong>they don't even own</strong>. See: "Diaspora Syndrome"</li>
  <li>When you delete the last comment of a ticket that has changed the title of that ticket, it doesn't revert the ticket's title</li>
  <li>There are currently 1,584 tags for Rails lighthouse alone. The problem here is that <strong>anybody</strong> can add a tag to a ticket. <strong>Most of the tags only have one ticket assigned to them.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>But ENTP won&#8217;t fix these issues. They have much more exciting products to work on now. It&#8217;s a product that was developed years ago and they have a tiny team working on maintaining it. This is sad, too.</p>

<p>The maintenance of the Rails lighthouse is non-existant. The maintenance of Lighthouse in general is almost non-existant. This makes me sad. These problems seem almost unfixable to me as a single person. But together, as a community, we can work on fixing the Rails Lighthouse.</p>

<p>Please, please, please: spend some time each week looking at the tickets on the Lighthouse. Do these things:</p>
<ol>
<li>You can be extremely helpful just by assigning tickets that need to be closed, resolved, wontfix'd or marked as duplicate to me or anybody else on the "Assigned to" list.</li>
<li> If you want to be extremely extremely helpful, verify that patches apply correctly and if you think that specific patch should be applied to Rails and you've tested it, give that ticket a +1. Once the ticket has 3 +1s, assign it to somebody on the "Assigned to" list who will then mark it as verified. This is the final step before it gets tested + merged by Core.</li>
<li> If it doesn't apply, just put a comment there explaining what broke and hopefully the OP will fix it.</li>
<li> If you think that the patch <strong>should not</strong> be applied to Rails, give the ticket a comment with "-1" at the start, and a reason for the "downvote". When a ticket receives 3 -1s, it will be marked as "wontfix".</li>
</ol>
<p>A little help here?</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gem Development Guide</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/gem-development-guide"/>
   <updated>2010-10-01T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/10/gem-development-guide</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href='http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/advanced-rails-documentation/'>my request yesterday</a> asking people what Rails documentation would be valuable, a large group of respondents said they&#8217;d like to see a guide on how to develop a gem. As I figured this would only take me two days to write and would be a good way to promote <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>a certain book</a>, I&#8217;ve begun writing one which I should have finished by tonight with only generators and releasing to cover.</p>

<p>You <a href='http://github.com/radar/guides/blob/master/gem-development.md'>can see it here</a>.</p>

<p>This is the kind of guide I was talking about in yesterday&#8217;s post. They don&#8217;t have to be short and they don&#8217;t have to be long, they just have to be <em>informative</em>. Is this what people would like to see more of? Are the topics I put forward yesterday worthwhile covering or is there something more interesting to the Greater Audience?</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Advanced Rails Documentation</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/advanced-rails-documentation"/>
   <updated>2010-09-30T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/advanced-rails-documentation</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I&#8217;ve been talking to a lot of people about Rails. It&#8217;s what I do. Lots of these people I talked to were in San Francisco when I was. Some others were in Jacksonville Beach. A common thread of conversation was that to truly know the Rails internals you have to read the source and interpret it for yourself what it means. If only there were guides out there for the more advanced concepts in Rails.</p>

<p>There was discussions as recently as March this year about starting up a Rails Internals documentation group, much in the same vein that docrails has people who write the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org'>Rails Guides</a>. These guides are top-notch and are a great boon to the resources of people who are just getting started with Rails, but there&#8217;s nothing comparable for those who are more advanced.</p>

<p>This is where the Rails Internals documentation comes in. It&#8217;s clear to me from the conversations I&#8217;ve had with people about Rails over the past couple of months that there&#8217;s a <strong>real need</strong> for some seriously good advanced documentation. There&#8217;s also the sidebar on <a href='http://yehudakatz.com'>Yehuda Katz's</a> blog for <a href='http://skribit.com'>Skribit</a>, where people can vote up posts they want Yehuda to write about. Yehuda&#8217;s too busy blowing our minds with other things (i.e. <a href='http://github.com/carlhuda/bundler'>Bundler</a> and now <a href='http://sproutcore.com'>SproutCore</a>) to write about them.</p>

<p>The highest request on that list is &#8220;migrating from rails 2.3.* to 3.0&#8221;, which is neatly covered by <a href='http://www.railsupgradehandbook.com/'>Jeremy McAnally's Rails 3 Upgrade Handbook</a>.</p>

<p>The second highest request on that list is &#8220;The lifecycle of a request through the rails stack&#8221;. This is an <strong>epic</strong> in itself. There&#8217;s an amazing amount of work that goes into rendering even a simple view through a controller, and that&#8217;s just the basic part of it. Your routes could route out to a Sinatra application, your model could actually be an ActiveResource model or a NoSQL model and you could be returning JSON data rather than an actual template.</p>
<h3>Fucking Rails man, how does it work?</h3>
<p>So I&#8217;ve been thinking for quite a while that it&#8217;d be nice to work on Rails documentation <strong>full time</strong>. Back in January when I was between jobs I begun writing the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/initialization.html'>Rails 3 Initialization Process</a> guide. I stopped writing it because I got a (kinda) paying gig writing <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>Rails 3 in Action</a>. I loved digging into the guts of Rails and explaining how they work. I got a great response from my initial postings of that guide and I&#8217;d like to complete it as the first in the Rails Internals Guides series, with the remainder beginning with:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Action Dispatch, receiving + serving requests</li>
  <li>Action Pack, finding controllers and response rendering</li>
  <li>Active Model, the different modules and how you can create your own ORM-like system</li>
  <li>Active Record, ARel &amp; things such as associations and dynamic finders</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides the &#8220;big picture&#8221;, I have no solid idea of precisely what would go in these guides, or even if they&#8217;re interesting to people outside the world of my own head.</p>

<p>Would I even be able to find a company to pay me to do this full-time? The biggest question is how it would benefit them. Wouldn&#8217;t it save time having some go-to place for Rails internals documentation so you don&#8217;t have to spend all that time trudging through it? I think so.</p>

<p>The second question: Is there a large enough audience interested in documentation in a similar vein to the <a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/initialization.html'>Initialization Guide</a>? Is that the &#8220;correct&#8221;/sensible way to do that? Is it useful?</p>
<strong>As a Rails programmer, what guides would you like to see written about Rails? It could just be about the ecosystem, not neccesarily the framework's code itself. Let me know in the comments.</strong>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>You suck.</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/you-suck"/>
   <updated>2010-09-24T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/you-suck</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The tense of the phrase &#8220;You suck&#8221; may not be the present. It may be the past. It may even be the future.</p>

<p>But face it: You suck. Right now.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m facing it too. I see people doing amazing things. Things like Facebook and LinkedIn know that, through some kind of complex association somebody who I&#8217;ve said as much as &#8220;hey&#8221; to could potentially be my friend. I don&#8217;t know how to do this, therefore I suck.</p>

<p>But let&#8217;s get back to you. At one point in the past, you decided you wanted to learn a language. Let&#8217;s, for the sake of the argument, say that this language is Ruby. You wrote a blogging application in Ruby on Rails and you thought you were top shit.</p>

<p>Then somebody else took a look at your code and their first reaction was to commit Seppuku.</p>

<p>Ok, maybe not that severe. But they didn&#8217;t have kind words.</p>

<p>A programming community is one of the harshest (non-weather-based) environments on the planet when you&#8217;re getting started. Just about everybody knows more than you do. They&#8217;ve been doing it for what seems like millennia and they&#8217;ve got the answer to every question you throw at them. If they&#8217;re patient, they&#8217;ll help you get going and perhaps give you pointers from time to time.</p>

<p>You&#8217;re still going to suck. You&#8217;ll gradually pick up things as you progress. Perseverance pays off in the end, but it&#8217;s a long way to travel. People will condemn and criticise you, your code and your coding practices. Others will be gentler. Stick with it.</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s say you&#8217;re a little peeved at the massive goliath that is Facebook and you want to create your own social networking application, but you&#8217;re going to make it distributed. Through some kind of magical process, you manage to acquire $200,000+ in funding to develop this from people just like you who don&#8217;t like Facebook and want an alternative.</p>

<p>Then, with this money, you develop it. You give it a cool name and the Internet Hype Machine does its thing. They expect it to be perfect, flawless in every way, shape and form. They expect you to be professional because they threw money at you. Little did they know that you don&#8217;t have all that much experience in developing. Your idea is solid, and you&#8217;ll learn what you need to as you go along.</p>

<p>Eventually you release a &#8220;Developer Preview&#8221; and that&#8217;s when things start looking stormy. People use words like &#8220;cesspool&#8221; to describe the quality of your code. Haters gonna hate.</p>

<p>Of course, by this point, you understand that I&#8217;m talking about Diaspora. There is <strong>so much hate</strong> on the intertubes about Diaspora right now. These four guys are not big players in the Ruby community. Their GitHub profiles have only a few projects on them. They are newbies to this wonderful world of Ruby and we, as stalwarts, need to play nice with the new kids on the block.</p>

<p>So how about this: instead of putting so much energy into hating Diaspora, how about you volunteer to help out? Oh, you don&#8217;t have time for that? Then shut the fuck up, armchair critic. These guys are working hard on their project, much like you are on yours.</p>

<p>At least, you would be if you weren&#8217;t hating on the new kids.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Need Newbies</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/need-noobs"/>
   <updated>2010-09-23T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/need-noobs</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not sure if I&#8217;ve mentioned this before but I&#8217;m writing <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>Rails 3 in Action</a> and what I haven&#8217;t mentioned before is that I need newbies.</p>

<p>Newbies are the lifeblood of the Ruby community and without them we wouldn&#8217;t have a solid foundation. A community without a healthy supply of newbies is a community <strong>that is dying</strong>.</p>

<p>Have you hugged your neighbourhood noob today?</p>

<p>The reason I need newbies is because I&#8217;ve got all these awesome reviewers, but most of them are <strong>experienced</strong> Rails developers who are probably assuming the same things I am when reading the book. Somethings to us <strong>just make sense</strong>. Newbies don&#8217;t have this ability yet, so I need a couple of people who are interested about learning Ruby on Rails to buy my book and give it a nice hard read. I need the newbies to be critical of everything they read. I need them to point out where a wall-o&#8217;-text would be better described in picture form and maybe even a quick sketch if they&#8217;re artistically inclined.</p>

<p>I am really appreciative of the current mob I have reviewing the book (and I&#8217;m not cheating on you!), I just need more newbies.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m going to need about 3 more people. These three newbies need to have enough spare time to be able to read the chapters as I&#8217;m progressing along with them and provide feedback. Question everything. Does it only make 99% sense? Question it.</p>

<p>In return, I&#8217;m told I give good, manly handshakes. I may give you one too. Alternatively if you prefer the whole monetary system, I will pay you the cost of the PDF / book and then maybe <strong>some more</strong>.</p>

<p>Who&#8217;s up for this? <strong>If you want to help, buy a copy of <a href='http://manning.com/katz'>Rails 3 in Action</a>, have a read and post any issues you encounter on the forums! Thanks!</strong></p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Fake Update</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/the-fake-update"/>
   <updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/the-fake-update</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s a fake update I emailed to my mum earlier today:</p>

<p>Last couple of days have been great :)</p>

<p>Caught up with some strangers who I met online, they lured me into a non-descript white van and blindfolded me and we are somewhere warm underground. The candy was delicious and they say they have more.</p>

<p>But first I have to go and run some &#8220;errands&#8221; for them around San Francisco which they say involves something called &#8220;weed&#8221; (I recommended they go down to the hardware store and get some spray, works well. They laughed.) and some other thing about &#8220;popping caps&#8221; into peoples asses. I&#8217;m no proctologist but they said they would give me training and the tools to do it. Not looking forward to that part but apparently that&#8217;s business.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s this one guy here who people are telling me he&#8217;s &#8220;the man&#8221; (at first I thought they were saying he is &#8220;a man&#8221; and I was all &#8220;duh, have you SEEN his Adams apple?&#8221; and they clarified that they meant he was a &#8220;pig&#8221;. Again I was all &#8220;duh, have you seen him eat?&#8221; and they just rolled their eyes and walked away) I am not sure why he is the man, I was just told never to say it to his face.</p>

<p>Anyway, gotta roll out now. Love you heaps and will send back some presents for you when I get some time off.</p>

<p>(and if it isn&#8217;t obvious yet, this is a big joke and shouldn&#8217;t believed by anyone to be real. I&#8217;ll send you a real update later on :)</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>pre-GoGaRuCo Summary</title>
   <link href="http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/pre-gogaruco-summary"/>
   <updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
   <id>http://ryanbigg.com/2010/09/pre-gogaruco-summary</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow is the first day of the two day GoGaRuCo conference here (gasp!) in San Francisco. This is mostly for my family / friends interested in what I&#8217;ve been doing in SF. Just a brain dump of what&#8217;s made an impact so far. It contains boring stuff.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s some photos <a href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/radarlistener/sets/72157624970572352/'>[1]</a> <a href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/radarlistener/sets/72157624973230930/'>[2]</a> I&#8217;ve been taking whilst I&#8217;ve been in San Francisco. So far it&#8217;s been a really good town and I could definitely get used to living in a place like this (without the fog though).</p>

<p>In general: everyone is nice. The people who are driving will stop (at stop signs) and wait for you to cross, not run them just as you&#8217;re crossing. Still getting used to looking over my left shoulder rather than my right for cars that are turning into where I&#8217;m crossing though. I&#8217;ll figure that one out by Sunday next week.</p>

<p>I arrived on Monday and I&#8217;m living with two people called Cecilia and Spencer who are really nice and have offered me a comfy couch to sleep on for a reasonable price per night and I&#8217;m content with that. The major problem is that it&#8217;s at the top of this massive hill which I must climb every time I come home, be it sober or not sober. That&#8217;d be &#8220;Monte Vista Avenue&#8221; in the photo sets. I had dinner with a Perth guy who was visiting called Matt at a restaurant called Roxanne on Powell in town. The restaurant people here are almost over nice, but again something I could get used to. Went home at about 9pm and slept like a log.</p>

<p>On Tuesday I caught up with Santiago Pastorino, one of the newest Ruby on Rails core members. He&#8217;s from Uruguay and professes not to know much English but we can have a conversation just fine. He brought a friend called Gilberto and we hung out for lunch. Later on, I went home to grab my laptop and then back into town to attend the Heroku/PostgreSQL talk which I enjoyed. Met up with somebody who recognised me from my Twitter avatar, Josh Kalderimis, a NZ guy. He thanked me for my efforts in the Ruby &amp; Rails communities and we chat for a while about Ruby / job things. There was also two other guys called Nick and Ken. Ken was about to launch a beta version of his startup and expressed interest in hiring someone with Ruby talent and I got his card. Also met Terence Lee who I know through using Heroku who is an absolute god when it comes to answering support tickets. Went out drinking at a bar that had a multi-page Scotch menu called Nihon and walked out without paying. Remembered 5 minutes later and turned around and paid for my drink + 20% tip for being an idiot. Call it a Stupid Tax. Trained it home and tackled the hill fine, again sleeping like a log.</p>

<p>On Wednesday, I was going to go to Fisherman&#8217;s Wharf but thought better of it when Cecilia said she hadn&#8217;t been in a while and wanted to go. I had also planned on meeting a friend that day near Palo Alto (south of the city, by Caltrain) but didn&#8217;t know if it was for lunch or dinner. I loitered around in town by hanging out in the Apple store and buying a traveller&#8217;s kit so I could finally charge my phone and then a universal adapter for my laptop from Walgreens so I could also charge that. I went to Borders to steal their WIFI (which is free and a practice I encourage all of Australia to take up) and charge up my phone. Ordered a &#8220;Regular&#8221; hot chocolate and got something that would pass as a regular-sized softdrink in Australialand. Drunk it all a little too quickly and felt a little sick after from all the sugar, but manned up and recovered.</p>

<p>Still on Wednesday (big day), I bought a &#8220;thank you&#8221; card for one of the people who got me into Rails, Ryan Ghods. Back when I was still &#8220;doing&#8221; PHP (I use &#8220;doing&#8221; loosely because nobody &#8220;does&#8221; PHP, PHP does you. Don&#8217;t use it.) Ryan was one of the people who showed me the Rails blog screencast tutorial (the original, with the &#8220;whoops!&#8221;) and suggested I get into it. I did and I have never looked back. I wrote in the card and headed down to Palo Alto where I figured I would meet my friend like I planned and now had a dual purpose of delivering this thank you card to Box.net. I completely underestimated how long the Caltrain would actually take to get there. I honestly thought it was closer to the city, but it felt like a 40 minute journey stopping all stations. During this time I&#8217;m trying to keep up Twitter correspondence with Box.net and asked if I could visit Ryan&#8217;s brother, Sam, who works for Box.net. Unfortunately it wasn&#8217;t to be and so I just dropped the letter in the letterbox outside. Hopefully it gets to The Other Ryan intact.</p>

<p>I retreated to the Starbucks nearby without a plan of what to do next and wrote a bitchy tweet about people not checking email/twitter because I hadn&#8217;t heard from my friend who wanted to meet me that whole week. Not 5 minutes later he sends an email to me and he says he&#8217;ll be at the Nuthouse down the road in 30 minutes. I head there and think that I deserve a cider, so I ask what brands they have. The waitress replies &#8220;Apple, Pear and Raspberry&#8221;. Oh. &#8220;Apple, please&#8221;, I say, sticking to my favourites. Later on I tried the pear one which is just as good, but Raspberry? I don&#8217;t know about that. So finally Matt (the friend) and I catch up at the Nuthouse and talk shop. He name drops that Mark Zuckerburg and his Facebook comrades drop in to the Nuthouse from time to time. My jaw drops. I am in the same bar that Mark Zuckerburg drinks at and the ciders are $3.75. Holy. Shit.</p>

<p>We end up going back to Matt&#8217;s place where I meet Walter, the hyper-hyper-hyper-hyper-active Border Collie and step in one of his &#8220;presents&#8221;. Matt gets some &#8220;scalding hot water&#8221; and I pour it on my shoe to wash it away. After learning my lesson, then I take off the shoe and the steaming sock underneath and scrub the shoe with a broom brush nearby. After that incident get in his car and drive to Stanford&#8217;s bookstore which is gigantic. I&#8217;ve never seen a bookstore with a cafe AND toilets AND three floors of books. Just massive. Matt casually mentions that Stanford receives &#8220;donations&#8221; from certain members of society and that a high-profile tech guy may be sending his son there. Stanford may have a new building dedicated to a special someone soon.</p>

<p>We spent the rest of the night at the Nuthouse eating peanuts (hence the name) playing Cricket (the darts version) and 501. Mark didn&#8217;t show, but there were Facebook people all chugging beer and chanting in a booth as we walked out. Is this the Web 2.0 bubble? I stayed the night at Matt &amp; Kyle&#8217;s house, sleeping on an air-mattress in their computer room. Slept incredibly well (which seems to be a pattern this entire trip)</p>

<p>Thursday (today), I met up again with Santiago and another guy I know from the Ruby community called Mislav with Cecilia in the San Francisco mall. Santiago wanted to spend the day hacking on the Rails source so we dropped him at the Starbucks nearby and Cecilia, Mislav and I went for a long walk all the way from the mall to Fisherman&#8217;s Wharf and then on to the Golden Gate Bridge. It was getting pretty evident we weren&#8217;t going to see anything when the fog started to come in but we went there anyway. We arrived back in town at about 8pm and Cecilia and I grabbed some food from the mall again whilst Mislav went off to drop off his bag. Cecilia left before I did as I planned to stick around and wait for word on pre-GoGaRuCo drinks but then I thought better of it and ended back at home writing this lengthy piece.</p>

<p>So what do I expect over the next few days? I expect to meet a lot of people who I&#8217;ve known for a very long time over the internet (Mum always said &#8220;don&#8217;t talk to strangers&#8221; and I may have selective hearing), much like I&#8217;ve already done in the past couple of days but on a much larger conference scale. I plan on listening intently to the talks, but they&#8217;re re-watchable online (eventually), whereas the social interaction isn&#8217;t re-playable.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s going to be great. I cannot wait. I cannot sleep. I am too excited. OK, maybe I can.</p>

<p>Just not right now.</p>]]></content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>